When looking at this irreplaceable, unique,
one ofa kind medieval city core,
dating back to the 9th century AD,
city leadership had asked themselves
acrucial question: where do I put my SUV?
Turns out, invaluable historical heritage sites
are the perfect places to store your car.
The romantic, millennium-old, winding streets
offer an exciting variety of parking spaces.
The centuries-old, baroque squares, formerly home
to bustling markets and high medieval culture,
are now proud displays of contemporary Prague culture.
The same can be said about the baroque sidestreets,
no less ornate than the squares. Offering
a window into the soul of 21st century Prague.
It has been said that Prague is
an utterly dysfunctional city,
unable to implement any positive changes;
with its Kafka-esque institutions
slowly collapsing under their own weight. This
is a false sentiment. Changes are, in fact,on the way.
For example, in terms of traffic policy, the
meeting to determine the date of the session,
on which they decide what cookies to serve on the
first twenty rounds of consultations before the
preliminary session preceding the initial rounds
of talks, is already scheduled for the year 2046.
In the meantime, Prague's castle remains a symbol of
the values and competence of its leadership.
But of course, Prague is more than
just a castle utilized as a parking lot.
On the other side of the Vltava river we see
Old Town. Behind it is New Town, named so
due to it having been built in the 14th century.
The two sides are linked by the famous CharlesBridge.
A masterpiece of baroque engineering and
architecture, built in 1402. Now, Prague’s
leadership had asked themselves: how could we best
utilize a medieval, six-centuries-old bridge in the 21st century?
Well, it turns out, six-centuries-old, UNESCO-protected
medieval bridges make for great covered parking lots.
We’re almost in Old Town. We just need to cross under
this exquisite baroque bridge tower overlooking
the baroque facades of Old Town,
right in front of the baroque pedestrian crossing.
The road we’re crossing right now is the famous
Smetana embankment. The presence of cars on this
road is a recurring point of conflict
between people and the city leadership.
Proponents of traffic calming had argued
that it's likely not a good idea to let a
dozen people in cars hold up hundreds
of pedestrians and tram passengers at a time.
The city leadership used to respond
to that argument that this state ofaffairs
is necessary, as those dozen drivers do not
have a convenient alternative route.
In order to solve this issue, a massive highway
tunnel complex was built under the castle, costing
2.7 billion dollars in today’s money. At long
last providing a quick, convenient alternative
to the embankment. Thus proponents of traffic
calming were able to once again raise the issue
of restricting car traffic on the embankment
in favor of public transit and pedestrians.
City Hall was quick to issue a
response to this renewed request,
later amending it with an additional
statement. It seems that limiting
car traffic on Prague’s Smetana embankment
will remain a task for future generations.
We penetrate into Old Town. Marveling at the
astounding architecture surrounding us. The
beautiful facades. Saint Clement’s Cathedral.
The Thai Massage Salon next to Saint Clement’sCathedral.
With a tasteful animatronic clown demon
above it, waving a flag that reads "I LOVE RELAX,"
with outdoor Christmas lights attached for better visibility.
However,as we were visiting during the off-season,
unfortunately we were unable to get the
full cultural experience this street offers.
This street is usually a great place to immerse
yourself in Prague culture. We are just
at the foot of Saint Clement’s Cathedral,
and behind me in the corner there is
a promotional riksha,
advertising the Thai massage salon by St Clement’s
Cathedral.
In this pedestrian zone there isusually a Dodge Ram
American pickup truckparked illegally
on most days of the year. Though it
doesn't seem to be here on this very day.
Walking down these historical streets, we are
enamored by the vibrant, authentic culture of
Old Town. Full of people: all of them locals
- in their respective home countries. Stores
line the streets, offering basic necessities for
daily life, like absinthe and foreign currency.
But this cultural epicenter of the Czech
Republic is not without its problems.
Short-term rentals on an industrial scale are
increasingly taking over the local housing market.
But what are the locals’ views
on the spread of AirBnB, and what
do they think of the rumors of eastern
oligarchs buying up the local housing stock,
to operate entire residential
blocks as short-term rentals?
These are the questions we wanted
to pose to Old Town's homeowners,
though unfortunately nobody on our
staff spoke Russian or Chinese.
We gradually leave the charm of Old
Town behind us as we enter New Town.
We eventually surface at Wenceslas Square:
the main public space of the Czech Republic.
The square is currently under reconstruction.
Before the works, the square functioned as the
nation’s main, ceremonial parking lot. Over
there we see the statue of Saint Wenceslaus,
scanning the square with a stern look. Meant to
symbolize the difficult, often futile search for a
free parking spot in Prague, when trying
to park your third car in the city center.
The reconstruction of Wenceslas Square will bring
back the tramline that used to extend all the way
to the bottom of the square, eliminated by Soviet
leadership in 1980. Following the reconstruction,
trams will return to the upper half of
the square; with plans to restore tracks
on the lower half having been successfully
blocked by Prague’s conservative leadership.
Beyond the statue of Saint Wenceslas stands
the Czech National Museum. In order to help
highlight this important building, a 6-to-8
lane urban freeway was built around it.
This is the North-South Prague urban freeway,
built by Soviets to make invasions easier,
in case locals start wantingthings
like freedom of speech or democracy. Now,
there have been multiple attempts to calm traffic
on this freeway, by reducing the number of lanes,
opponents of traffic calming however argue,
that reducing the number of lanes on this highway
built by the Czechoslovakian Communist
Party would be an instance of Communism.
A stateless, classless road with no currency.
This road had been the site to numerous protests
by Last Generation Prague, advocating for a city-wide 30km/h
speed limit. Their actions would see
one of the six-to-eight lanes closed from traffic during
rush hour, leading to a massive traffic jam,
affecting thousands of average, working people.
Although their protests are a rareoccurrence,
we seemed to be in luck.
And yes, ladies and gentlemen, we seem to be
in luck, there does seem to be a protest
by Last Generation Prague just over there,
we were this lucky to have caught it, just at
this time. So we are going to go check it out.
We rush to the scene, hoping to
catch these selfish, narcissistic
scum red-handed. These vile eco-fascists,
selfishly holding up thousands of regular,
working people in traffic jams during rush hour.
So we've been looking for the Last Generation
protesters right here, but we can't seem to findthem,
even though the highway is completely
congested. So we believe that these green
communists have changed tactics in the meantime,
opting to show up for their protest in their cars
instead of on foot. Truly a vile display of
selfishness from these radical activists.
Recovering from the experience, we decide to
calm our nerves with culture. Lucky for us,
just on the other side of the urban freeway
stands the Czech National Museum's newbuilding.
Would you like to visit the Czech
National Museum just over there? This way!
This passageway leads not just to the Czech
National Museum, but also to the Czech National
Opera. Julius Caesar in Egypt, I hear, is the
latest opera piece that can be viewed there.
And there we can already see the yellow columns,
those are the Czech National Opera. Behind it is
the Czech National Museum's new building,
so just through this underpass. Careful,
there are puddles of feces all around. That column
is used as a public toilet as we can see. And it
smells like that too. Just so we can reconnect to our
core, human, primal nature before witnessing the
most important cultural relics of the Czech
Republic. And/or an opera piece, just overthere.
Here we can see the opera visitors have
left a can of Pilsner Urquell on the sidewalk.
They must have been in a hurry. Always be on
time when going to an opera, as it's considered
to be very bad manners to be late. And you might
even have to throw away your beer can on the way.
Once you're done enjoying the greatest cultural
relics and artifacts of the Czech Republic,
you can continue your cultural experience
here, on the outside. Looking at this
SUV parked in the forbidden zone. Over there
there is a Smart car advertising a nightclub [strip club],
which has been left here for quite some time as
we can see. There are stickers on the window,
on the other side there are tags, and
there is dust collecting all over theplace.
And just over there, there is the
rent-a-Hummer, a promotional Hummer which
has been left there for the past two years,
to advertise a rental service locally.
Wwe head out towards the center of New
Town in search of greener pastures.
We are in Prague’s 2nd district, on
I.P. Pavlova square, where the Prague
2nd District city hall had come up with
an ingenious urban planning solution,
to be studied by urban planners across the globe.
The car-centric pedestrian zone.
But this isn’t the only instance of
Prague’s urban planning brilliance by far.
We’re standing on Horní street,
in Prague’s 4th district. Where,
in 2022, the local [district] city hall had turned most
of this sidewalk into a parking lot,
thereby gaining 15 additional parking spaces,
arguing that locals wanted more parking spaces.
The locals had filed a lawsuit against the
Fourth District city hall, looking to take
back their sidewalk from cars. Their lawsuit
was successful, with the court ordering city
hall to eliminate the parking spaces.
But this was not the end of the story.
City hall has held firm in opposition to the
locals' opposition to adding more parking spaces,
arguing that the locals needed more
parking spaces. They consequently
tried to reintroduce sidewalk parking
in defiance of the court's decision.
Locals sued city hall again, with the court
ordering city hall for the second time to
remove parking spaces from the sidewalk. It
remains to be seen what city hall will do next.
Will Prague 4's city hall be
able to enact the people's will,
even against the people's
will? Only time will tell.
But other Prague districts have been
far more creative in their quest
for the creation of more urban
parking lots in the year 2025.
We are now in the 15th district of Prague,
on Sáňkařská street. Over here we can see
a number of ingenious solutions enacted by
the local city hall to increase the number
of parking spaces. So as a first step, the
sidewalks on both sides were eliminated,
and turned into parking spaces. And just
to the left of me, which is your right,
there is a children's playground and some trees.
The children's playground will be eliminated,
and these trees will be cut down in
order to create even more parking spaces,
to incentivize an even greater use of automobiles.
By the elimination of the children's playground
and the cutting down of the trees, the
district will gain 23 new parking spaces.
Locals have created a petition against
the measure, already passed by city hall.
It remains to be seen if Prague 15 will be
more successful than Prague 4 in enacting the
people's will against the people's will. But
turning sidewalks and children's playgrounds
into parking lots are not the only measures
Prague has in store for us. A further pillar
of Prague's urban planning policy is the
complete lack of traffic rule enforcement.
The threat of actually enforcing the
rules of the road has naturally made a
lot of middle-aged men in large,
expensive cars extremely upset.
They worry that if the rules of the road
suddenly applied to them as well, then lively
streets such as this one would turn into urban
hellscapes, like the ones in Amsterdam or Vienna.
However, some locals continue to entertain
notions, such as: drivers should abide by
the rules of the road; further polarizing society
by putting themselves in opposition to those who
want to ignore [the rules]. In order to resolve this
conflict, a compromise was struck by Prague's
city hall. On one hand, drivers can break any
traffic rule with impunity. On the other hand,
pedestrians, cyclists and public transit
users may shut up. Still, many of Prague's
drivers continue to complain that they are, in
fact, being oppressed. Drivers in Prague are
indeed so oppressed, that illegal drag races
in the city center can only be held at night,
whereby contestants block the main urban
freeway leading into the center. The police
haven't yet mustered the courage to intervene,
preferring to watch from a safe distance.
Parking, traffic calming and pedestrian safety
aren't the only hot button issues in Prague,however.
A further tumultuous point
of contention is the question of
urban cycling. Up until recently, plotting
a safe bicycle route through Prague was
a task impossible for average people.
However, technology has now made this
possible, as long as one can afford
processing time on the IBM mainframe.
Prague urban planning works much like
alchemy, in that if you create something good,
another good thing of equal value must be
taken away. So here, in front of Prague's
second largest railway station, the city had
created a pedestrian zone using these bollards,
which is only occasionally violated
by drivers. And so in exchange,
in the next street over there, a bike lane
was taken away to make more space for cars.
Yet another defeat for Stalinism in Prague, the
City of Progress. Of course, when Joseph Stalin
first began building safe, separated bike paths in
1924, nobody could have suspected that those are,
in fact, precursors to a totalitarian empire.
Thankfully, Prague's leadership is always on edge,
determined to stop such evils from
ever setting foot within city limits.
It's time for us to leave, so we
head to Prague's Central Station,
scheduled to be reconstructed sometime
within the next 5 to 50 years. To that end,
a large part of the currently indoors
passenger hall is to be demolished,
to give way to a massive, open-air wooden
pergola. However, some have questioned the design.
Thankfully, the concept of "weather"
as such does not exist in Prague,
with every single day of the year being a very
pleasant 20°C, slightly sunny, and no wind.
I think the most frustrating thing about
Prague for me personally, is that everything
is given for a great city, for an absolutely
great city. The buildings are beautiful,
the landmarks are there, it has plenty
of history going back hundreds of years,
and yet, when you look around on the streets,
the city itself does not seem to acknowledge the
fact that only about a quarter of its residents
drive a car on on a day-to-day basis. If you look
at the average Prague streetscape, you would
think that 90% of citizens drive a car. That
is absolutely not the case. And I think Prague
should take more steps to make its public spaces
more fair. But of course the reason why Prague
does not look like Vienna or Amsterdam has its
own political reasons. The city leadership,
where conservatives are in the majority,
have been blocking every single initiative
to make the city more pedestrian-friendly,
cycling-friendly or even to just prioritize public
transit, so that two people in cars cannot hold
up two-to-three hundred in trams or buses. All
of these measures, that would make Prague a more
western city, have been consistently vetoed by the
conservative - I suppose - majority. If Charles IV
came back today, and looked at the current, sorry
state of Prague, Charles IV could not make it to
Prague Castle on the Royal Path. He would get run
over. The current urban planning status quo in
Prague is fundamentally anti-human, anti-culture,
anti-history. Look at the castle. Look at the
state of Old Town, and especially New Town. Cars
parked everywhere, all the streets are congested,
dangerous, kids cannot be let go on bicycles
alone, which is a standard in every single western
capital, western city. Most of these places are
just three or four bollards away from becoming
really quality, human friendly areas. The city
is under conservative leadership. Conservative
parties seem to hate walkable, cycling-friendly,
pedestrian-friendly urban planning styles. Their
ideal world is one where the inner city is just
an AirBnB desert. It's just a short-term rental
wasteland, full of tourists, no one else, no
locals. And everyone is living outside in the
suburbs, in the satellites, in these tiny, cheap
bungalows, and everyone commutes in by car and
then leaves in the evening. This has a number of
notable negative effects on society. It atomizes
people, it atomizes society. Just individuals and
families, as Margaret Thatcher would say. And I
don't want anyone to take this as me [maliciously]
criticizing Prague or [maliciously] criticizing
the Czech people. That is not my goal at all.
I would like to help improve things, because
obviously, so far nothing has helped in Prague.
I believe in a better Prague, and I believe,
consequently, in a better Czech Republic. And
I think one of the roads towards that is sound
urban planning policy, Which is the exact opposite
of what Prague is doing right now. And my hope is, that
someone waking up finally in city hall, and
realizing that this cannot go on any further,
things need to change. And that in the end, we
will see a Prague which is truly a western city,
as opposed to something out of a
postcard of 1970s Turkmenistan.